{"tossups": [{"question": "This action was supported by Eduardo Frei\u2019s Christian Democratic Party and occurred after sweeping gains for one leader\u2019s party in midterm elections. The target of this event gave a radio broadcast that he ended with the words \u201cLong live the people! Long live the workers!\u201d, then used a gold-plated AK-47 to commit suicide while barricaded in La Moneda Palace. For ten points, name this event that led to the rise of the military dictator Augusto Pinochet.", "answer": "<b> overthrow</b> of Salvador<b> Allende</b> (accept<b> death</b> of Salvador<b> Allende</b>; accept descriptions of a<b> coup</b> d\u2019etat against Salvador<b> Allende</b>; accept descriptions of the<b> 1973 Chile coup</b> d\u2019etat; accept descriptions of \u201cthe<b> coup</b> d\u2019etat that brought Augusto<b> Pinochet</b> to power\u201d before his name is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In the 1971 edition of this game, success was determined by how fast and accurately they typed words like \u201cBANG\u201d or \u201cWOW.\u201d MECC produced this game, in which taking the Barlow Road or floating across the Columbia River Gorge are the two options for players as they approach Willamette Valley. The player is responsible for leading for leading a wagon party starting at Independence, Missouri in, for ten points, what classic educational computer game that shares its name with a pioneer route?", "answer": "The<b> Oregon Trail</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was appointed king by Mongol ruler Sartaq Khan and died shortly after traveling to Sarai to pay tribute. This man thwarted Hermann of Dorpat from capturing Pskov during a battle in which the lake Peipus had frozen over. Before that battle against the Teutonic Knights, this man rose to fame defending Novgorod against the Swedes. For ten points, name this ruler of Kiev known for a victory on Lake Peipus at the Battle of the Ice.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Nevsky</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this US state, Augustus Stinchfield partnered with a British man to form a private medical practice. Miners flocked to this state following a discovery in its Vermilion Range. Charles Alfred Pillsbury founded his namesake company in this state, where its flour mills competed with rival General Mills. Iron ore from mountains in this state was transported by train to cities like Duluth. The Mayo Clinic was founded in Rochester in, for ten points, what US state where 3M is headquartered in a suburb of St. Paul?", "answer": "<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Resistance against Nazi occupation in this city was led by an organization whose logo was the letters\u201cPW\u201d in the shape of an anchor, the AK or Home Army. Mikhail Tukhachevsky was defeated outside this city by Jozef Pilsudski in the \u201cMiracle on the Vistula.\u201d The Z.O.B. led a revolt in this city that was defeated by Jurgen Stroop, after which most of the Jewish Combat Association was deported to Treblinka. For ten points, name this city whose ghetto underwent a major revolt in 1943 in Poland.", "answer": "<b> Warsaw</b> (or<b> Warszawa</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a battle during this campaign, the<em> USS Choctaw</em> was hit more than fifty times without suffering any casualties. This campaign included the Battle of Snyder\u2019s Bluff and a battle where troops marching up Rodney Road were attacked by the forces of John Bowen, the Battle of Port Gibson. This campaign\u2019s most famous battle ended with the surrender of John Pemberton on July 4th. The Army of the Tennessee fought in, for ten points, what Grant-led Union campaign named for a Mississippi city that was besieged in 1863?", "answer": "<b> Vicksburg</b> Campaign Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this denomination practice the Arba\u2019een pilgrimage, which is the largest religious gathering on earth, in the city of Karbala. That pilgrimage takes place forty days after a holiday on which this denomination mourns the death of Husayn, the day of Ashura. This denomination includes the Sevener and Twelver sub-sects. For ten points, name this denomination of Islam, the majority in Iran and the second largest after Sunni.", "answer": "<b> Shia</b> Islam (or<b> Shiite</b>s; or<b> Shia</b>s; prompt on Islam before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This battle began when one side took a stand a Mozhaysk, refusing to follow Barclay de Tolly\u2019s advice to retreat. Utitsa village was burned to the ground after it exchanged hands multiple times in this battle. The losing side in this battle sought to defend the Raevsky redoubt. After defeating Mikhail Kutuzov, this battle\u2019s victors entered Moscow, only to find it empty. For ten points, name this 1812 victory for Napoleon on Russian soil.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Borodino</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This modern state was home to a colony where Thomas Morton brewed beer and erected a maypole for a multiracial population, Merry Mount. Mary Dyer was executed in this modern state, where the Antinomian Controversy in this state was begun by Anne Hutchinson. Cotton Mather presided over a series of trials in this state that began with the accusation of the Barbadian slave Tituba. For ten points, name this modern state in which the Salem Witch Trials took place.", "answer": "<b> Massachusetts</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A refusal to recognize this country was maintained in the Hallstein Doctrine until the Basic Treaty normalized relations. The Monday Demonstrations led to the downfall of one of this country\u2019s leaders. Its leaders included Egon Krenz, Erich Honecker, and Walter Ulbricht, and its secret police under Marcus Wolf closely collaborated with the KGB. For ten points, name this country that constructed the Berlin Wall to bar migration to its western neighbor.", "answer": "<b> East Germany</b> (or the<b> G</b>erman<b> D</b>emocratic<b> R</b>epublic; accept<b> D</b>eutsche<b> D</b>emokratische <b>R</b>epublik; prompt on Germany)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man briefly retired to Caprera, an island he partially owned, after he was wounded and captured at the Battle of Aspromonte. This former schoolmaster worked for the Republic of Rio Grande do Sul in his early career, granting him the nickname \u201chero of two worlds.\u201d This man was victorious at the Battle of the Volturnus, which came near the end of his Expedition of the Thousand. For ten points, name this commander of the Redshirts, a hero of Italian unification.", "answer": "Giuseppe<b> Garibaldi</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a film from this country, the title character is created by a clerk\u2019s typo; that film\u2019s score was composed by the composer of the</b><em><b> Scythian Suite</b></em><b>. Another composer from this country dedicated a string quartet, which opens with a (+) DSCH motif, \u201cto the victims of fascism and war;\u201d that composer from this country also featured an \u201cinvasion\u201d theme and a theme from his opera (*)</b><em> Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District</em> in his<em> Leningrad Symphony</em>. For ten points, name this home country of Sergei Prokofiev and Dmitri Shostakovich.", "answer": "<b> Soviet Union</b> (or<b> USSR</b> or<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b>; accept<b> CCCP</b> or <b>Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik</b>; prompt on Russia) (2) <b>In this country, a siege against a native earthen fort known as the \u201cBat\u2019s Nest,\u201d</b> <b>Ruapekapeka. Fortifications known as</b><em><b> pa</b></em><b> were defended in a series of wars in this country, which contains the Bay of Islands. In this country\u2019s settlement of Russell, the chopping down of a (+) pole holding the Union Jack instigated an 1845 war in which Hone Heke [hoh-nay hay-kay]</b> <b>fought. Another conflict in this country began after they started to acquire (*) </b>muskets from merchants based in nearby Sydney. The Maori fought the British and each other in, for ten points, what country where the British founded cities like Wellington? ANSWER:<b> New Zealand</b> (accept<b> Aotearoa</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Foreign protectorates in this country included Cochinchina and Annam. France\u2019s</b> <b>control of this country was confirmed in the 1885 Treaty of Tientsin. The Japanese</b> <b>supported (+)</b> <b>Bao Dai, who gave this country its modern name after Vichy</b> <b>administrators were removed but abdicated in 1945. The Geneva Accords divided this</b> <b>country after the Battle of (*)</b> Dien Bien Phu, a victory for Ho Chi Minh. French Indochina included Laos, Cambodia, and, for ten points, what Southeast Asian country with capital at Hanoi?", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> (prompt on French Indochina before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}